Inventory of the Leonid Andreyev miscellaneous papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Leonid Andreyev miscellaneous papers
1900-1922
89037
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 2 card file boxes (1.2 linear feet)
Plays, poems, short stories, letters, and photographs relating to Russian literature and drama, and to conditions in Russia during World War I. Includes diary of Anna Andreeva, wife of Leonid Andreyev. In part, photocopy. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Andreyev, Leonid, 1871-1919.
Andreeva, Anna.
Access
Box 1 is open for research. Boxes 2 and 3 are closed; digital use copies available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1989.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternative Forms of Material Available
The color slides in box 1, folder 18 are reproductions of the glass autochromes in Boxes 2 and 3 (see the Container List below for details). Digital reproductions made from the color slides are also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Location of Originals
In part, originals in: T͡Sentralnyĭ gosudarstvennyĭ arkhiv literatury i iskusstva SSSR, Moscow.
Biographical Note
Russian novelist.
Scope and Content of Collection
Plays, poems, short stories, letters, and photographs relating to Russian literature and drama, and to conditions in Russia during World War I. Includes diary of Anna Andreeva, wife of Leonid Andreyev. In part, photocopy.
Russian literature.; Russian drama.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.
- Correspondence, 1913, undated (Box-folder 1: 1)
  Arrangement note
  Arranged chronologically.
- Diary of Anna Andreeva, 1920-1922 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  Scope and Contents note
  A notebook with handwritten entries, written in chronological order.
- Speeches and Writings, 1902-1918, undated (Box-folder 1: 3-16)
  Typescripts with handwritten notes, arranged alphabetically.
  - Bel'giitsam, undated (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Chest', undated (Box-folder 1: 4)
  - Dnevnik pisatelia v voinu 1914 goda, undated (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Dni nashei zhizni, 1908 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Iskrennii smekh, 1910 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Kon' v senate, undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
  - Mladost', undated (Box-folder 1: 9)
  - Pessimist, undated (Box-folder 1: 10)
  - Pis'ma o teatre, 1912 (Box-folder 1: 11)
  - Pis'mo L.N. Andreeva v gazetu 'Birzhevye vedomosti', 1918 (Box-folder 1: 12)
  - T'ma i noch', 1907 (Box-folder 1: 13)
  - V sei groznyi chas, undated (Box-folder 1: 14)
  - Zakon i liudi, 1902 (Box-folder 1: 15)
  - Miscellany (Box-folder 1: 16)
    Loose pages of typescripts and of photocopies of manuscripts.
- Photographs, undated (Box-folder 1: 17)
  Six black-and-white prints, most of them images of Andreyev, arranged generally in their original order.
- Color Slides, circa 1900-1919 (Box-folder 1: 18)
  Twenty-six photographic copies of glass autochromes in Boxes 2 and 3, including images of Andreyev, his family, and landscapes, arranged generally in their original order. Digital use copies of these color slides also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
  - Baby seated in wicker baby carriage, circa 1900-1919
  - Bearded man seated at table with patterned tablecloth, circa 1900-1919
    Possibly Andreyev or a family member.
  - Bearded man seated next to pile of books, circa 1900-1919
  - Boats moored to forested shore, circa 1900-1919
  - Buildings flanking river with stone bridge in background, circa 1900-1919
  - Buoys hanging above water, circa 1900-1919
  - Child in hat standing on porch and smiling, circa 1900-1919
  - Child seated in chair in middle of dirt pathway, circa 1900-1919
  - Child wearing hat and sitting on grass with rocky outcropping in distance, circa 1900-1919
    Possibly an Andreyev family member.
  - Corner of room with chair and framed picture, circa 1900-1919
  - Leafy tree on grassy lawn with body of water in the distance, circa 1900-1919
  - Little boy sitting among flower bed along path, circa 1900-1919
  - Man seated outdoors, circa 1900-1919
  - Man standing on rocky outcropping and looking away from camera, circa 1900-1919
  - Posed people in horse-drawn sleigh on snow, circa 1900-1919
    Possibly members of the Andreyev family.
  - Rocky shoreline, circa 1900-1919
  - Rutted dirt road leading to large building on horizon, circa 1900-1919
  - Small child standing outdoors in heavy coat and winter cap, circa 1900-1919
  - Snow around edge of building, circa 1900-1919
  - Stone structures (ruins?) along roadway, circa 1900-1919
  - Two little boys seated outdoors, circa 1900-1919
    Possibly Andreyev family members.
  - Two people in distance along shore of lake, circa 1900-1919
  - Two women standing in front of ruins, circa 1900-1919
  - White, columned building through trees, circa 1900-1919
  - Woman in hat seated by window, circa 1900-1919
    Possibly an image of an Andreyev family member.
- Color Glass Autochromes, undated (Boxes 2-3)
  Access
  Boxes 2 and 3 are closed.
  Twenty-six autochromes, including images of Andreyev, his family, and landscapes, arranged generally in their original order. Photographic slide copies are available in box 1, folder 18; digital use copies also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org. Each autochrome contains two almost identical images; the photographic slide copies and digital use copies capture the better of the two images.
  - Nineteen color glass single-image autochromes (1-7, 10-13, 16-18, 20, 22, 25, 26, 30) (Box 2)
  - Seven color glass double-image autochromes (8/24, 9/28, 14 a/b, 15 a/b, 19/23, 21/27, 29 a/b) (Box 3)